Jonathan Cram

Personal Details

Basic facts Staying in touch

Date of birth: 5 February 1978 Website: ultrathings.com
Address: 62A Attwood Close Mobile: 0791 431 6684

Basingstoke

Basingstoke Email: jon@ultrathings.com RG21 8YY

Nationality: British GitHub: github.com/webignition

Profile

I am an agile, pragmatic web-oriented software developer capable of implementing and maintaining applications regardless of the technology stack, currently loving PHP development utilising Symfony2, composer, git, PHPUnit, Jenkins and Travis CI.

I have released 48 open-source composable PHP packages which have in total been installed more than 230.000 times.

I have a 1st class honours degree in Internet Engineering, my own profitable self-bootstrapped automated web testing service, a decade of commercial web development experience and a continued enthusiasm to build awesome web software.

Technology Overview

Languages: PHP, JavaScript, Java, Groovy, Ruby

Web: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript

Frameworks: Symfony2, Bootstrap, Nodejs, Rails, Grails

Testing: PHPUnit, PhantomJS, CasperJS, Jenkins, Travis CI

Server configuration: Apache2, Nginx, MySQL

Relevant Experience

Founder and Lead Developer, Simply Testable (Web Testing Startup) June 2012 - Present

I founded and continue to develop SimpyTestable.com, a one-click automated web testing and code quality analysis service.

I develop primarily within the PHP Symfony2 framework, utilising a range of composable packages to interact with a range of open-source third-party testing tools.

The system comprises a collection of applications communicating asynchronously over HTTP to coordinate distributed testing and to optimise test throughput dynamically based on demand.

Senior Web Developer, Limegreentangerine October 2011 - June 2012

Within a close organisation of 7 employees, I consulted with clients on needs and requirements, assisted print-oriented designers in adapting to web-focussed projects and translated designs and requirements into functional content-driven web sites.

I introduced an internal build system comprising developer-specific local environments, automated local test deployments, git for version control and Jenkins for standard continuous integration as well as for the running of a set of generic web page quality tests.

Software Developer, Box UK September 2009 - October 2011

I worked closely with design, UX and QA teams to deliver great services, handcrafting both frontend and backend functionality, utilising mostly HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, ExtJS, PHP, Doctrine, Rails, Ruby, Grails, Groovy and Java. ORM layers keep the SQL at bay but when these abstractions leak I'm perfectly comfortable delving into MySQL and MSSQL guerying.

I lead the development of a new learning resource repository for the Learning Skills and Improvement Service (LSIS). Practical constraints led to the use of Grails, a rapid framework I had not previously used and which I mastered during the six-week project.

I worked with World Vision US on worldvisionmicro.org. The client is in the US and development in the UK; I'm perfectly capable of working within a distributed environment.

Hosting Reborn (Web Hosting Startup) June 2006 - January 2015

I developed hostingreborn.com, the UK's first true pay-as-you-go web hosting provider. The system adds a service layer on top of a cluster of Linux servers, presenting the user with a simple, usable, accessible web interface for creating and managing web hosting accounts.

I sold the service in January 2015 to focus efforts on newer projects.

Education

Internet Engineering BEng (1st Class Honours) 2005 - 2009 Brunel University, Uxbridge, Middlesex

I achieved an average mark of 83% across a multidisciplinary course bringing together skills in computer systems, web application development, multimedia content delivery, network design and network security. My final year project involved pioneering research into web application messaging efficiency and how people perceive delays.

HND Computing 1997 - 1999 University of Wales Institute Cardiff, University of Wales, Cardiff

Main areas of study involved program design, project management, programming methodologies, practical programming in C++, Visual C++ and Visual Basic, database design through data structure analysis, database implementation directly on an SQL server and through Microsoft Access and general IT skills such as word processing and spreadsheets.